Ogden M. Pleissner
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ogden M. Pleissner papers
1928-1976
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Pleissner, Ogden M.
3.2 linear feet
The papers of painter Ogden M. Pleissner measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1928-1976. Found within the papers are biographical material, scattered letters, artwork, nine scrapbooks, over one foot of printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
Ogden M. Pleissner donated his papers to the Archives in 1972 and 1976.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Ogden Minton Pleissner was born on April 29, 1905 in Brooklyn, New York, son of George W. and Christine Minton Pleissner. He began his education at the Brooklyn Friends School. One summer while a teenager, he was sent to Charlie Moore's ranch in Dubois, Wyoming, in order to improve his health. During pack trips, camping, and trout fishing in Yellowstone Park and the Buffalo Forks country, Pleissner became devoted to the outdoor life, developing his skills as a hunter and fisherman. He began drawing images of horses, cowboys, Native Americans, and scenery and realized that his interest in art was strong enough to pursue it in school.
From 1924 to 1927 Pleissner attended the Art Students League in New York, studying under George Bridgman and Frank V. DuMond. Pleissner continued his studies with DuMond in Cape Breton, where he also met Mary Corbett whom he married in 1929. In the following year, Pleissner held his first solo exhibition at the Macbeth Gallery in New York. Although he maintained a studio in New York City, Pleissner and his wife spent many summers in Wyoming, later expanding their travel to Europe.
In 1940 Pleissner was elected a National Academician. Two years later, he was commissioned by the U.S. Office of Emergency Management on the advice of the Section of Fine Arts to visit various war industries to make a group of 10 paintings depicting the work in these plants.
In 1943, Pleissner was commissioned as Captain in the Army Air Forces to work as an artist with the Historical Division, painting a record of the Air Force activities. After training, he was deployed to Anchorage, Alaska, and from there he visited many of the Aleutian Islands. Due to lack of funding, his original mission was changed, and he was put on inactive duty in November 1943, in order to continue his work as a War Art Correspondent for Life magazine. This allowed him to complete his paintings of the Aleutian Islands. In the spring of 1944, he flew to headquarters in London, England, later following the Normandy invasion through northern France, he painted scenes from the critical battle at St. Lo. In the summer of 1945, Life magazine sent him on a tour of Europe to make a series of paintings of the most significant battle sites, including Omaha Beach, Remagen, and Anzio.
During his post-war career, Pleissner participated in many organizations, including his service as vice-president of the National Academy of Design, director of the Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, and trustee at the Shelburne Museum in Vermont. He was also a member of the Salmagundi Club, the National Arts Club, and the Brooklyn Society of Artists. His work is in the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Brooklyn Museum, and the Philadelphia Museum.
In the 1970s Pleissner traveled extensively in Europe and spent summers at his studio in Pawlet, Vermont.
Ogden M. Pleissner died of a heart attack on October 24, 1983 in London, England.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter Ogden M. Pleissner measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1928-1976. Found within the papers are biographical material, scattered letters, artwork, eight scrapbooks, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical material includes Pleissner's U. S. Army Certificate of Service, an autobiographical essay, and miscellaneous notes. Scattered letters dating from 1942-1976 primarily concern Pleissner's service in the U. S. Army. There are also letters from colleagues and friends including artists Harrison Cady and Stow Wengenroth.
Nine scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scattered letters from art organizations and colleagues including Juliana Force, Charles Vezin, and Stow Wengenroth. An additional 1.2 linear feet of printed material consists primarily of clippings, and exhibition catalogs and announcements. Also found within the papers is one etching, and photographs of Pleissner, his colleagues, exhibitions and artwork.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Art and war
Types of Materials:
Scrapbooks; Photographs
Names:
Cady, Harrison, 1877-1970; Wengenroth, Stow, 1906-; Force, Juliana, 1876-1948; Vezin, Charles, 1858-1942
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series. All series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1943-1971 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1942-1976 (Box 1; 13 folders)
Series 3: Art Work, undated (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1930-1953 (Boxes 1-2; 29 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1928-1975 (Box 2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1958-1974 (Boxes 3-4; 31 folders)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1943-1971, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Biographical material consists of a U.S. Army Certificate of Service, an award certificate, and a curriculum vitae. Also included is an autobiographical typescript About the Artist and miscellaneous notes including hunting score cards decorated with reproductions of Pleissner's art work.
  - Certificates and Curriculum Vitae, 1943-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescript and Miscellaneous Notes, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters, 1942-1976, Series 2:; (Box 1; 13 folders)
  Letters primarily concern Pleissner's service in the U. S. Army. There are also scattered letters from colleagues and friends including artists Harrison Cady and Stow Wengenroth, and Texas Governor John Connally.
  - Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Letters, 1945, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Letters, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Artwork, undated, Series 3:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Artwork consists of an etching depicting an ancient European street with overhanging buildings.
  - Etching, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Scrapbooks, 1930-1953, Series 4:; (Boxes 1-2; 29 folders)
  This series consists of unbound scrapbook pages containing clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, miscellaneous printed material, and three photographs of artwork. There are also scattered letters from art organizations and colleagues including Juliana Force, Charles Vezin, and Stow Wengenroth. Scrapbook 8 contains an exhibition catalog, The Army at War, illustrated with photographs of artists on the battlefield.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1930-1932, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1932-1934, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1935-1936, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1936-1940, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1937-1939, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-33)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1939-1944, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-37)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1941-1945, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1946-1953, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- Printed Material, 1928-1975, Series 5:; (Box 2; 1.2 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material including a book, Air War Against Hitler's Germany, that contains illustrations by Pleissner.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1946, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Clippings, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1948, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Clippings, 1949, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Clippings, 1950, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Clippings, 1951-1954, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
  - Clippings, 1956, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Clippings, 1958, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Clippings, 1959, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Clippings, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1962, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Clippings, 1963-1968, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-42)
  - Clippings, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
  - Clippings, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1928-1933 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 52-56)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1951, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 57-58)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1962-1963, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1967-1970, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Programs, 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Brochure for the Art Students League, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Catalogs for Artwork, 1947-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Booklet Significant War Scenes by Battlefront Artists, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Booklet Michigan on Canvas, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Book Air War Against Hitler's Germany, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Book Directory of Honorary Appointments, Smithsonian Institution, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Photographs, 1958-1974, Series 6:; (Boxes 3-4; 31 folders)
  Photographs are of Pleissner, his colleagues, exhibition installations, and artwork. There are also two unbound albums containing photographs of artwork
  - Photographs of Pleissner, 1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Pleissner with Colleagues, 1958-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photograph Album 1 of artwork, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-29)
  - Photograph Album 2 of artwork, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 30-35)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Artwork, undated, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 36-42)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Artwork, undated, (10 folders) (Box 4 (pam), Folder 1-10)